var questions = [
  {//1
	type: "multiple-choice",
	question: "Which of the following benefits is <b>MOST</b> important for senior management to understand the value of governance of enterprise IT? It allows senior management to:",
	options: [
		"understand how the IT department works.",
		"make key IT-related decisions.",
		"optimize IT resource utilization.",
		"evaluate business continuity provisions."
	  ],
	answer: 1,
	justification: [
		"A. Understanding how the IT department works is the responsibility of the chief information officer (CIO). However, senior management should understand the role of IT.",
		"B. When senior management understands the benefits of governance of enterprise IT as well as new technologies and challenges, they act as informed decision makers and take ownership of IT-related decisions.",
		"C. Optimizing IT resource utilization is a subset of how the IT department works and is, therefore, the responsibility of the CIO.",
		"D. Evaluating business continuity provisions is an operational responsibility of senior management."
	],
  },
  {//2
	type: "multiple-choice",
	question: "Which one of the following is the BEST indicator of good governance practice?",
	options: [
		"The IT risk register is well maintained.",
		"The IT policies and procedures are well maintained.",
		"The IT strategic plan is developed with the business.",
		"The board is regularly briefed on IT."
	  ],
	answer: 3,
	justification: [
		"A. The risk register is maintained by the management function and is only a partial view of risk, not a holistic view of IT, which is needed for governance.",
		"B. Maintenance of IT policies and procedures is a management function approved by the board.",
		"C. The IT strategic plan is developed with the business and submitted to the board for approval and is considered a long-term plan that describes how IT resources will contribute to the enterprise’s strategic objectives (goals).",
		"D. For effective monitoring by the board, it is important that the board be briefed regularly on IT functions. This will give the board the opportunity to evaluate and direct."
	],
  },
  {//3
	type: "multiple-choice",
	question: "Which of the following is the MOST significant trigger for a chief executive officer to consider a high-level review of IT governance practices?",
	options: [
		"Absence of documented policies",
		"Lack of IT standardization",
		"Failed IT initiatives",
		"Lack of a formal system development life cycle methodology"
	  ],
	answer: 3,
	justification: [
		"A. Policies are the overall intention and direction as formally expressed by management. A lack of documented policies may lead to failed IT initiatives but would not be the biggest trigger to review IT governance practices",
		"B. IT standardization is the process to agree on specifications for an IT product or process to be repeatedly and consistently used within the enterprise. Standardization can help with operational repeated processes, which would be the focus of the chief information officer and not a trigger for the chief executive officer to consider a high-level review.",
		"C. Failed IT initiatives are cost drivers to the enterprise as a whole and impact the business processes as well as their automation. When an IT initiative fails, it can have a major impact on the entire business and its profitability.",
		"D. The lack of a formal system development life cycle methodology is not a major trigger but may also lead to failed IT initiatives"
	],
  },
  {//4
	type: "multiple-choice",
	question: "Which of the following BEST helps determine enterprise architecture by providing guiding principles?",
	options: [
		"The IT steering committee",
		"The IT strategy committee",
		"The board of directors",
		"The chief information officer"
	  ],
	answer: 1,
	justification: [
		"A. The IT steering committee implements the IT strategy developed by the IT strategy committee using guiding principles.",
		"B. The IT strategy committee is responsible for providing guiding principles for a business-aligned IT strategy through the enterprise architecture (EA).",
		"C. The board of directors provides input for business strategy and IT strategy.",
		"D. The chief information officer is responsible for developing the IT EA using guiding principles"
	],
  },
  {//5
	type: "multiple-choice",
	question: "Which of the following would PRIMARILY create transparency in the IT decision-making process as part of governance of enterprise IT?",
	options: [
		"Stakeholder-approved roles, responsibilities, goals and metrics are promptly communicated.",
		"The progress reporting process of service delivery is clearly established.",
		"Communication of decisions to IT employees is clear.",
		"Balanced scorecard results are promptly communicated to the enterprise."
	  ],
	answer: 0,
	justification: [
		"A. Transparency would be created by communicating stakeholder-approved roles, responsibilities, goals and metrics to the enterprise. This allows everyone to understand the basis for the decisions being made.",
		"B. Progress reporting reflects the advancement of the execution but does not provide information about the basis of the decision.",
		"C. Communication of decisions to employees is one piece of the process to create transparency in IT decision making.",
		"D. The balanced scorecard provides information about how IT is performing according to the approved goals."
	],
  },
  {//6
	type: "multiple-choice",
	question: "The GREATEST benefit of strong IT governance processes is:",
	options: [
		"improved productivity and a greater ability to respond to business needs.",
		"increased accountability and a greater ability to respond to compliance requirements.",
		"more effective incident and problem management.",
		"better IT investments and a greater adaptability to changing technology sophistication."
	  ],
	answer: 0,
	justification: [
		"A. When IT services are properly aligned with business strategy as a part of IT governance, the result is higher productivity and a greater ability to respond to business requests. Alternatively, productivity and the ability to respond to business needs are drivers to the establishment of strong IT governance processes.",
		"B. Accountability and the ability to respond to changing compliance requirements are specific business needs, not the overall objective of IT governance.",
		"C. While incident and problem management are likely to be improved through strong IT governance, the two processes do not reflect the pervasive and holistic nature of effective IT governance.",
		"D. Better IT investments and adaptability to changing technology sophistication are not indicators of strong IT governance in an enterprise."
	],
  },
  {//7
	type: "multiple-choice",
	question: "The PRIMARY focus in effective organizational change enablement of a governance of enterprise IT implementation should be on:",
	options: [
		"documenting the what and how of the change.",
		"clarifying the reason to change.",
		"communicating the vision.",
		"demonstrating achieved results."
	  ],
	answer: 1,
	justification: [
		"A. The what and the how of the change describes the impact of the change to the organization. However, the what and the how may not be effective if the why is not understood.",
		"B. The first action should be to work on the motivation of people by explaining the reasons why the change is necessary.",
		"C. Communication of the vision facilitates understanding of the change in roles and responsibilities for individuals. This can only be done when the reason for change has been defined.",
		"D. Demonstrating achieved results to the organization shows the enterprise’s ability to run change programs effectively. This is a normal activity as the enabled change progresses toward its objectives."
	],
  },
  {//8
	type: "multiple-choice",
	question: "While implementing IT governance within an enterprise, the PRIMARY focus must be on the objectives of:",
	options: [
		"the enterprise.",
		"the stakeholders.",
		"the business function.",
		"IT management."
	  ],
	answer: 1,
	justification: [
		"A. Enterprise objectives are driven by stakeholder objectives.",
		"B. Enterprises exist to create value for their stakeholders.",
		"C. Business function objectives are outcomes of enterprise objectives.",
		"D. IT management’s objectives are derived from enterprise and business function objectives"
	],
  },
  {//9
	type: "multiple-choice",
	question: "Which of the following facilitates strategic alignment?",
	options: [
		"Business owner sponsorship of projects",
		"A business impact analysis",
		"Alignment of the IT budget to strategic objectives",
		"Project monitoring"
	  ],
	answer: 0,
	justification: [
		"A. The primary task of strategic alignment is identifying the IT strategy and goals that support the enterprise business strategy. Business owners reflect the business expectation for service and levels of satisfaction and, thereby, identify alignment needs.",
		"B. A business impact analysis (BIA) is an exercise that determines the impact of losing the support of any resource to an enterprise, establishes the escalation of that loss over time, identifies the minimum resources needed to recover and prioritizes the recovery of processes and the supporting system. BIAs do not facilitate strategic alignment between IT and the business.",
		"C. Alignment of the IT budget to strategic objectives is achieved indirectly by aligning IT strategic goals to business strategic goals. It does not facilitate the alignment process but is a result.",
		"D. Project monitoring is an operational activity and does not directly relate to strategy management and/or strategic alignment."
	],
  },
  {//10
	type: "multiple-choice",
	question: "Which of the following practices BEST reduces resistance to organizational change?",
	options: [
		"Continued stakeholder involvement",
		"Proactive communication",
		"A clear definition of the desired state",
		"Customized employee training"
	  ],
	answer: 0,
	justification: [
		"A. It should not be assumed that the various stakeholders involved in, or impacted by, new or revised enablers will readily accept and adopt the change. The possibility of ignorance and/or resistance to change needs to be addressed through continued stakeholder involvement, which helps in the governance transparency process.",
		"B. Proactive communication is an important enabler, but does not by itself lower resistance to change, particularly when the target audience (stakeholder) has not already been involved.",
		"C. A clear definition of the desired state is important, but without continued stakeholder involvement, resistance to achieving the desired state may remain.",
		"D. Customized employee training helps communicate the change according to the target audience’s needs and preferences but is not as helpful as continued stakeholder involvement."
	],
  },
  {//11
	type: "multiple-choice",
	question: "Which one of the following tools is the MOST effective to communicate with the board of directors about the business value of IT?",
	options: [
		"Internal rate of return",
		"IT balanced scorecard",
		"Return on investment",
		"Process capability assessment"
	  ],
	answer: 1,
	justification: [
		"A. The internal rate of return (IRR) is a measure of the expected profitability of an investment. IRR will only look at the financial benefits but will not consider intangible benefits.",
		"B. The balanced scorecard (BSC) gives the balanced view of the total value delivery of IT to the business by incorporating both tangible and intangible values that the business wants to know. BSCs translate strategy into action to achieve goals with a performance measurement system that goes beyond conventional accounting, measuring those relationships and knowledge-based assets necessary to compete in the information age: customer focus, process efficiency and the ability to learn and grow.",
		"C. Return on investment is the measure of operating performance and efficiency, computed in its simplest form by dividing net income by the total investment over the period being considered. Thus, it is more of a financial review tool than a balanced view for the board.",
		"D. Process capability assessments provide important information on the capability of IT processes to meet their intended purposes. However, they answer the question “Are we doing things right?”—not the question “Are we doing the right thing?”—and thus do not communicate the value of IT as well as the ITBSC."
	],
  },
  {//12
	type: "multiple-choice",
	question: "Which of the following BEST helps an enterprise plan for IT investments?",
	options: [
		"Enterprise architecture",
		"Risk assessment reports",
		"Audit recommendations",
		"Emerging technologies"
	  ],
	answer: 0,
	justification: [
		"A. Enterprise architecture (EA) involves the structured documentation of an enterprise’s IT assets and processes representing both current state and desired future state, and thus facilitates planning for IT investments.",
		"B. Risk assessment reports will report on the risk based on the EA but are not the best document to determine IT investments.",
		"C. Audit recommendations may drive IT investments, particularly from a risk management perspective; however, they do not provide a holistic view of the company’s IT investment portfolio.",
		"D. Emerging technologies will be useful, but may not be the best solutions based on the current EA."
	],
  },
  {//13
	type: "multiple-choice",
	question: "Which of the following BEST describes the purpose of adopting and implementing enterprise architecture (EA)?",
	options: [
		"EA facilitates communication.",
		"EA facilitates decision making.",
		"EA facilitates business agility.",
		"EA facilitates mergers and acquisitions."
	  ],
	answer: 1,
	justification: [
		"A. EA provides a framework for ensuring that the enterprisewide goals, objectives and policies are properly and accurately reflected in decision making related to IT systems. Facilitating communication is a benefit of implementing EA but is not the main purpose for implementation.",
		"B. Enterprise architecture (EA) is a description of the fundamental underlying design of the IT components of the business, the relationships among them and the manner in which they support the enterprise’s objectives. EA facilitates the decision-making process by providing a road map that can guide future technology investments to ensure IT alignment with the business and value delivery. It provides structure for facilitating change management, informed decision making and communications.",
		"C. Business agility is the ability of a business to adapt rapidly and cost efficiently in response to changes in the business environment. Business agility is the outcome of organizational intelligence, which can only be built if the enterprise has an EA framework in place to build the intelligence required.",
		"D. EA may help to facilitate mergers and acquisitions, but this is not the main purpose of implementation."
	],
  },
  {//14
	type: "multiple-choice",
	question: "To BEST support the enterprise’s business goals, the IT department should:",
	options: [
		"respond to governance requirements in alignment with board direction.",
		"ensure transparency and understanding of IT costs, benefits, strategy, policies and service levels.",
		"respond to business requirements in alignment with the business strategy.",
		"make sure that IT services are available as required."
	  ],
	answer: 2,
	justification: [
		"A. Responding to governance requirements is an important IT goal that can only be achieved after an alignment with the business strategy and requirements.",
		"B. Ensuring transparency is an important IT goal that can only be achieved after an alignment with the business strategy and requirements.",
		"C. The IT department must do all of these things, but responding to business requirements in alignment with the business strategy is the best choice to support the business goals.",
		"D. IT service availability is an operational goal, defined by availability requirements based on business needs."
	],
  },
  {//15
	type: "multiple-choice",
	question: "An enterprise is planning to implement a framework for IT governance to align IT and business strategy. Which dimension of the IT balanced scorecard will this strategic initiative primarily be linked to?",
	options: [
		"Financial",
		"Internal",
		"Customer",
		"Learning and growth"
	  ],
	answer: 1,
	justification: [
		"A. Implementing a framework for IT governance targets internal processes rather than the financial dimension of the balanced scorecard (BSC). The financial dimension helps in achieving a financial outcome and answers the question “To satisfy our stakeholders, what financial objectives must we satisfy?”",
		"B. The internal processes dimension of the IT BSC is aimed at effectiveness through a structured approach and IT governance standards such as ISO 38500—International Standard for Corporate Governance of Information Technology (IT Governance) and frameworks such as COBIT. When implemented as a strategic project, it will be linked to the internal process dimension of the IT BSC.",
		"C. Implementing a framework for IT governance targets internal processes and is not directly linked to the customer dimension of the IT BSC. The customer dimension answers the question “To satisfy our financial objectives, what customer needs must we satisfy?”",
		"D. Implementing a framework for IT governance targets internal processes and is not directly linked to the learning and growth dimension of the IT BSC. The learning and growth dimension answers the question “To achieve our goals, how must we learn and innovate?”"
	],
  },
  {//16
	type: "multiple-choice",
	question: "The parameters used to determine whether a system development project can be outsourced should PRIMARILY be documented in the:",
	options: [
		"IT investment plan.",
		"resource availability plan.",
		"IT strategic plan.",
		"enterprise IT policy."
	  ],
	answer: 2,
	justification: [
		"A. IT investment plan in incorrect. The IT investment plan is a subset of the IT strategic plan.",
		"B. The resource availability plan will identify the availability of existing resources.",
		"C. The IT strategic plan is a long-term plan (i.e., with a three- to five-year horizon) in which the business and IT management cooperatively define how IT will contribute to the enterprise’s strategic objectives (goals). The IT strategy should include parameters for outsourcing for the enterprise.",
		"D. The enterprise IT policy is an overarching document that provides direction for IT and may not include all the parameters for outsourcing."
	],
  },
  {//17
	type: "multiple-choice",
	question: "Which of the following BEST provides an internal control environment?",
	options: [
		"Processes that ensure specific outcomes",
		"Procedures that prescribe specific tasks",
		"Automated processes that avoid human error",
		"Roles and responsibilities that establish accountability"
	  ],
	answer: 0,
	justification: [
		"A. Processes that ensure specific outcomes constitute a strong internal control environment.",
		"B. Procedures are components of the governance framework, yet are only effective if they are designed to ensure a specific outcome.",
		"C. Automated processes that prevent or detect undesirable events are components of the governance framework but are not as comprehensive as well-designed and well-executed processes that ensure specific outcomes.",
		"D. Roles and responsibilities are components of the governance framework but are not as comprehensive as well-designed and well-executed processes that ensure specific outcomes."
	],
  },
  {//18
	type: "multiple-choice",
	question: "Information security governance awareness is BEST established when:",
	options: [
		"senior management is supportive.",
		"data ownership is identified.",
		"assets to be protected are identified.",
		"security certifications are issued."
	  ],
	answer: 1,
	justification: [
		"A. The best way to increase awareness in the enterprise is through guaranteed senior management championship.",
		"B. Data ownership identification is a necessary, but not sufficient, component to ensure information security governance awareness.",
		"C. Asset protection is an operational mechanism to support data ownership.",
		"D. Security certification is an operational mechanism to support asset protection."
	],
  },
  {//19
	type: "multiple-choice",
	question: "Which of the following roles should make final data access decisions for a critical project?",
	options: [
		"Data owners",
		"Project managers",
		"Senior management",
		"Database administrators"
	  ],
	answer: 0,
	justification: [
		"A. Data owners are in the best position to decide about access, based on the person’s role andresponsibilities.",
		"B. Project managers are responsible for the development and successful execution of a project plan to meetproject deliverables (scope) within time and budget.",
		"C. Senior management is accountable for overall IT implementations but will not be involved in data accessdecisions.",
		"D. Database administrators have data custodian responsibilities: storing and safeguarding computerized datain alignment with data owner directives."
	],
  },
  {//20
	type: "multiple-choice",
	question: "Which of the following benefits is the MOST important reason for using an IT balanced scorecard?",
	options: [
		"Strategic alignment with the business",
		"Quantification of costs and benefits",
		"Identification of tangible and intangible benefits",
		"Performance measurement"
	  ],
	answer: 0,
	justification: [
		"A. The balanced scorecard (BSC) was initially developed as a performance management system that helps enterprises to drive their strategies and measurement. More recently, the BSC has been applied to IT and has brought about the IT BSC that can be linked to the business BSC, and in this way it can support IT/business governance and the alignment process.",
		"B. Quantification of costs and benefits only reflects a limited view of the value that can be delivered by IT.",
		"C. Identification of tangible and intangible benefits is included in the BSC; however, it is only a part of the process for strategic alignment with the business.",
		"D. Less successful investments may affect benefits at the bottom of the enterprise significantly, but not provide benefits at the top of the enterprise. An IT BSC is a way to measure/manage organizational performance, while performance measurement is a tool for more effective management. The results of performance measurement will tell what happened, not why it happened or what to do about it."
	],
  },
  {//21
	type: "multiple-choice",
	question: "Effective governance of enterprise IT requires that:",
	options: [
		"the IT strategy be an extension of the enterprise strategy.",
		"the enterprise strategy be an extension of the IT strategy.",
		"IT governance be independent of enterprise governance.",
		"investments in IT be made to obtain competitive advantage."
	  ],
	answer: 0,
	justification: [
		"A. Effective IT governance requires that IT and business move in the same direction; the IT strategy is required to be aligned with the enterprise’s overall business strategy. Each IT goal must clearly align with an enterprise goal.",
		"B. The IT strategy is an extension of the enterprise strategy and must clearly support stakeholder needs.",
		"C. IT governance is not an independent discipline; it must be fully integrated into the enterprise’s overall governance.",
		"D. Investment benefits cannot be optimized if investments in IT are based purely on obtaining competitive advantage. The investment portfolio must balance benefits realization as well as risk and resource optimization."
	],
  },
  {//22
	type: "multiple-choice",
	question: "When a new IT governance policy has been approved, it is BEST to:",
	options: [
		"have an independent party sign off.",
		"conduct a walk-through exercise.",
		"prepare a communication plan.",
		"update the IT strategy accordingly."
	  ],
	answer: 2,
	justification: [
		"A. Sign-off by an external party, when appropriate, should occur prior to approval.",
		"B. Conducting a walk-through based on the revised policy should occur prior to approval.",
		"C. When a document, such as a policy, has been updated, it is good practice to communicate those changes throughout the organization.",
		"D. Relevant policy changes should be incorporated into the IT strategy, which should be included in the communication plan."
	],
  },
  {//23
	type: "multiple-choice",
	question: "The effectiveness of IT governance is BEST determined by:",
	options: [
		"evaluating activities of the board’s IT oversight committee.",
		"determining the percentage of projects delivered on time and within budget.",
		"evaluating stakeholder satisfaction.",
		"complying with international standards."
	  ],
	answer: 2,
	justification: [
		"A. Evaluating activities of the board’s IT oversight committee will determine the extent of involvement of the board in the process of IT governance; however, evaluating stakeholder satisfaction directly provides better insight into the effectiveness of IT governance.",
		"B. Determining the percentage of projects delivered on time and within budget helps to determine stakeholder satisfaction; however, it is not a holistic view.",
		"C. IT governance is the responsibility of executives and the board of directors and consists of the leadership, organizational structures and processes ensuring that enterprise IT sustains and extends the enterprise’s strategies and objectives.",
		"D. Complying with international standards may be a good practice but does not ensure stakeholder satisfaction."
	],
  },
  {//24
	type: "multiple-choice",
	question: "Which of the following BEST enables a successful implementation of IT governance?",
	options: [
		"IT steering committee involvement",
		"Chief information officer sponsorship",
		"Board direction mandate",
		"Quarterly IT management meetings"
	  ],
	answer: 2,
	justification: [
		"A. IT steering committee involvement supports the implementation of IT governance, but board direction and mandate are more important.",
		"B. Chief information officer (CIO) sponsorship occurs at a lower level within the enterprise; clear direction from the highest level of the enterprise is crucial for successful IT governance implementation.",
		"C. The direction for IT governance implementation must come from the highest level of the enterprise—from the board.",
		"D. Quarterly IT meetings are important for reporting and monitoring purposes but are not the most important enabler of a successful implementation of IT governance"
	],
  },
  {//25
	type: "multiple-choice",
	question: "Which of the following is the PRIMARY reason for defining and managing the enterprise IT strategy?",
	options: [
		"It has become an industry standard.",
		"It directs short-term IT goals.",
		"It improves the efficiency of IT services.",
		"It contributes to business value."
	  ],
	answer: 3,
	justification: [
		"A. IT is part of the business strategy.",
		"B. Short-term IT goals will be defined by the long-term goals in the IT strategy.",
		"C. Improving efficiency of IT services is part of the IT strategy execution.",
		"D. The enterprise IT strategy must be aligned with business objectives, which focus on value delivery to stakeholders."
	],
  }
]